Alice Yamin
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Alice Yamin papers
1927-1998
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Yamin, Alice
2.0 linear feet
The papers of painter, draftsperson, and art consultant Alice Yamin date from 1927-1998, and measure 2.0 linear feet. Found within the papers are letters from artists, writers, galleries, and CIGY-GEIGY Corporation for whom Yamin worked as an art consultant. The collection also contains exhibition files, printed material, and photographs of Yamin, family members, and colleagues.
Provenance
The Alice Yamin papers were donated in 1981 by the artist and in 2002 by Harry Smith, her nephew.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Alice Bernard was born on April 8, 1905 in Paris, France. She was brought to the United States as a child and spent most of her life in New York City. She married writer Leo Yamin who died on January 20, 1999.
Alice Yamin was a painter and draftsperson influenced by Abstract Expressionism. Beginning in 1950, she worked with a carbon medium, primarily producing dramatic black and white works on paper. She was also an art consultant for the international chemical firm CIBA-GEIGY Corporation that began collecting contemporary art in 1959 when it moved its headquarters from Manhattan to Ardsley, New York, a suburb of New York City.
Alice Yamin died on April 4, 2002.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter, draftsperson, and art consultant Alice Yamin date from 1927-1998, and measure 2.0 linear feet. Found within the papers are letters from artists, writers, galleries, and CIGY-GEIGY Corporation for whom Yamin worked as an art consultant. The collection also contains exhibition files, printed material, and photographs of Yamin, family members, and colleagues.
The most significant series consists of letter files, which also contain scattered printed material and photographs collected by Yamin, concerning specific individuals and organizations. Represented within the files are artists Herb Aach, Ilya Bolotowsky, Ernest Briggs, Lily Brody, Fritz Bultman, Elaine DeKooning, Sideo Fromboluti, Fritz Glarner, Adolph Gottlieb, John Grillo, Buffie Johnson, Alex Katz, William H. Littlefield, Alice Trumbull Mason, Elizabeth McFadden, Daphne Mumford, Barnett Newman, Philip Pavia, Mark Rothko, Elsa Schmid, and Jane Teller; curator Henry Ginsburg; writers Barbara Nimri Aziz, Georgine Oeri, Gertrud Oeri-Sarasin, and Leo Yamin; and galleries including the Ingber Gallery and the Landmark Gallery. There are also letter files concerning the CIGY-GEIGY Corporation; for Alice Yamin's brother, businessman Frank S. Bernard, and the town of Chilmark, Massachusetts, where the Yamins spent their summers. Even though Yamin's responses to the letters are not included in the collection, this series illustrates the wide range of her friendships and associates in the art business.
Also found are exhibition files containing letters, prospectuses, business records such as loan agreements, clippings, and exhibition announcements and catalogs concerning the inclusion of Yamin's art work primarily in group exhibitions. Printed material consists of miscellaneous clippings, and exhibition announcements and catalogs that do not relate to the exhibition files, as well as miscellaneous booklets, brochures, and a copy of the book American Drawings, Watercolors, Pastels, and Collages published by the Corcoran Gallery of Art which contains a reproduction of Yamin's work. Photographs are of Yamin, family members, and colleagues including Bill and Maria Lipkind, and Aaron Siskind.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 4 series. Letter files pertaining to specific individuals and organizations are arranged alphabetically; miscellaneous letters, exhibition files, printed material, and photographs are arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Letter Files, 1927-1998 (Boxes 1-2; 1.5 linear feet)
Series 2: Exhibition Files, 1956-1982 (Box 2; 18 folders)
Series 3: Printed Material, 1949-1992 (Box 2; 22 folders)
Series 4: Photographs, 1923-1978 (Box 2; 2 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Lipkind, Bill; Lipkind, Maria; Siskind, Aaron
Subjects-Topical:
Painting -- New York (State) -- New York; Consultants -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Draftsman -- New York (State) -- New York
Types of Materials:
Photographs
Names:
Aach, Herbert, 1923-1985; Aziz, Barbara Nimri; Bernard, Frank S.; Bolotowsky, Ilya, 1907-; Briggs, Ernest, 1923-; Brody, Lily; Bultman, Fritz, 1919-1985; De Kooning, Elaine; Fromboluti, Sideo, 1921-; Ginsberg, Henry; Glarner, Fritz, 1899-1972; Gottlieb, Adolph, 1903-1974; Grillo, John, 1917-; Johnson, Buffie; Katz, Alex, 1927-; Littlefield, William Horace, 1902-1969; Mason, Alice Trumbull, 1904-1971; McFadden, Elizabeth; Mumford, Daphne, 1934; Newman, Barnett, 1905-1970; Oeri, Georgine; Oeri-Sarasin, Gertrude; Pavia, Philip; Rothko, Mark, 1903-1970; Schmid, Elsa, 1897-; Teller, Jane; Yamin, Leo; Landmark Gallery (New York, N.Y.)
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Letter Files, 1927-1998, Series 1:; (Boxes 1-2; 1.5 linear feet)
  Miscellaneous letters from various individuals, galleries, and corporations discuss art-related topics including the purchase of Yamin's work and her participation in fund raising and political events. The files also contain scattered printed material and photographs. Represented are: artists including Ilya Bolotowsky, Ernest Briggs, Fritz Bultman, Elaine DeKooning, Adolph Gottlieb, Buffie Johnson, Alex Katz, Barnett Newman, and Mark Rothko; curator Henry Ginsburg; writers Barbara Nimri Aziz and Leo Yamin; and galleries including the Ingber Gallery and the Landmark Gallery. The file for Henry Ginsburg contains a photograph of Ginsburg with Queen Elizabeth II. There are also letter files concerning Markus Low of the CIGY-GEIGY Corporation; Alice Yamin's brother, businessman Frank S. Bernard; and the town Chilmark, Massachusetts, where the Yamins spent their summers.
  The files are arranged in alphabetical order, except for miscellaneous letters.
  - Miscellaneous Letters, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1953-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1963-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Herb Aach, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Mary Abbott; Ruth and Dick Abbott, 1958-1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ruth Abrams; American Federation of Arts; Anne Arnold, 1965-1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Alice Baber; Ed Baynard; Dick Bellamy, 1974-1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Victoria S. Benham and Charles N. Haas, 1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Thomas Hart Benton, 1975-1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Frank S. Bernard, 1959-1977, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Elizabeth Bettman, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - James Bohary, 1968-1994, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Ilya Bolotowsky; Louise Bourgeois, 1974-1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Warren Brandt, 1972-1991, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Ernest Briggs, 1960-1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Lilly Brody; James Brooks; Fritz Bultman, 1970-1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Gretna Campbell, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Chilmark, Massachusetts, 1960-1994, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
  - Alan Cohen, 1975-1991, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 31-32)
  - Gloria Cortella, Inc., 1976 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Rosemary Cove, 1976-1993 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Elaine DeKooning; Charles Duback; Edward Dugmore, 1974-1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Shannon Dunn; Max Eastman, 1972-1991 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Martha Edelheit, 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Natalie Edgar; Edward Farber, 1959-1994 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Herbert Ferber, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - John Ferren; James Frank, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Joseph Freeman and Charmion Von Wiegand, 1958-1977 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Sideo Fromboluti, Tillie Speyer, and Nora Speyer, 1961-1998, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 42-45)
  - Henry Ginsburg, Carl Ginsburg, and Cora Ginsburg, 1963-1996, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 46-47)
  - Fritz Glarner, 1969-1975 (Box 1)
  - Adolph Gottlieb, 1947-1984, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 49-50)
  - John Graham; John Grillo; Philip Guston, 1978-1982 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Clinton Hill; Nancy Hoffman Gallery; Bud Hopkins, 1973-1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Joan Hoberg-Petersen; John Hultberg; Julie Hyman, 1991-1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Barbara Ingber and Ingber Gallery, 1979-1992, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 54-55)
  - Buffie Johnson, 1973-1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Howard Kanovitz, undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Alex Katz, 1959-1987, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 58-59)
  - Lila Katzen; Don Kimes, 1981-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Phyllis Kimmel, 1976-1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Bill King, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Betty Klavun, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Al Kotin; Harry Kramer, 1965-1988 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Irving Kriesberg and Barbara Nimri Aziz, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Stanley Kunitz, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Landmark Gallery, 1959-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Fay Lansner, 1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - LGolda Lewis, 1986-1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Daphne Ley, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Linda Lindeberg; Maria Lipkind, 1971-1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - William H. Littlefield, 1956-1976 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Jon Loew; Michael Loew, 1957-1979 undated (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Markus Low, 1967-1994, undated, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 74-77)
  - Mildred Low; Oscar Magnan, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Nicholas Mariscano and Merle Mariscano, 1963-1980 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Alice Trumbull Mason, 1973-1993 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Jason McCoy, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Elizabeth "Sitty" McFadden Concerning Anne Ryan, 1971-1986, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 82-84)
  - George McNeil; Jay Milder; Robert Motherwell, 1970-1993 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Daphne Mumford, undated (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Michael Nadel, 1927-1989, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 87-88)
  - Cynthia Navaretta, 1973-1984 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Jean Neininger, 1965-1983, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 90-91)
  - Barnett Newman, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Georgine Oeri and Gertrud Oeri-Sarasin, 1946-1976 (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Ray Parker, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Philip Pavia, 1981-1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Marilyn Pearl Gallery; Philip Pearlstein, 1983-1992, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Vita Petersen; Richard Pousette-Dart, 1970-1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Jody Rapée (Joellen Hall); Milton Resnick; Lynne Rish, 1958-1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Ce Roser, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mark Rothko, 1961-1979, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - Judith Rothschild, 1973-1995, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 11-13)
  - Ruth Wolfe Rovinsky, 1971-1993, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Paul Russoto, 1981-1995, undated, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 15-18)
  - Elsa Schmid; Lillian Schreiber; Lynn Schreuer and Carlos Krish, 1965-1993, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Barbara Schwartz, 1973-1976 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Anita Shapolsky Gallery; Rose Slivka, 1979-1993 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Harry C. Smith, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Phoebe Sonenberg, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Bernice Steinbaum Gallery, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Carmen Suhear; Frances Taylor, 1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Jane Teller and Walter Teller, 1952-1993, undated, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 26-29)
  - Ruthven and Joellen Todd; Jack Tworkov, 1954-1969 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Esteban Vicente, 1982-1993 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Hugo Weber, 1970-1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Julian "Weissman; Pennerton West, 1974-1994 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Douglas Wirls; Elaine Gale Wrong, 1986-1993, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Leo Yamin, 1947-1995, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
  - Miscellaneous Yamin Family Members, 1965-1995, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Exhibition Files, 1956-1982, Series 2:; (Box 2; 18 folders)
  Exhibition files contain letters, prospectuses, business records, clippings, and exhibition announcements and catalogs concerning the inclusion of Yamin's art work, primarily in group exhibitions.
  - Lower East Side Independent Artists Exhibition, New York, New York, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - College Museum Exhibition, Hampton Institute, Hampton, Virginia, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Art East '66, New York, New York, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Gay Head Art Auction, Martha's Vineyard, Massachusetts, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Week of the Angry Arts Collage of Indignation, New York University, New York, New York, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Art East '67, New York, New York, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Art East '68, New York, New York, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Drawing Benefit for New York Studio School, New York, New York, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Color, Light, and Image, Women's Interart Center, Inc., New York, New York, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - 118 Artists, Landmark Gallery, Inc., New York, New York, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Drawing Benefit for New York Studio School, New York, New York, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Ten Artists, Landmark Gallery, Inc., New York, New York, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Works on Paper from the CIBA-GEIGY Collection Traveling Exhibition, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - 118 Artists, Landmark Gallery, Inc., New York, New York, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Clayworks Benefit Exhibition, New York, New York, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - 118 Artists, Landmark Gallery, Inc., New York, New York, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Heresies Benefit Exhibition, Grey Art Gallery, New York, New York, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Solo Exhibition in the Drawing Room, Landmark Gallery, Inc., New York, New York, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Printed Material, 1949-1992, Series 3:; (Box 2; 22 folders)
  Printed material consists of miscellaneous clippings, and exhibition announcements and catalogs that do not relate to the exhibition files, as well as miscellaneous booklets and brochures.
  - Clippings, 1949-1956 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Clippings, 1962-1966 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Clippings, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Clippings, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Clippings, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Clippings, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Clippings, 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Clippings Concerning the Care and Repair of Miscellaneous Items, 1979-1992, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1964-1969 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others, 1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Book American Drawings, Watercolors, Pastels, and Collages, Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Miscellaneous Booklets, 1966-1973, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 74-75)
  - Miscellaneous Brochures, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1966-1966 (Box 2, Folder 77)
- Photographs, 1923-1978, Series 4:; (Box 2; 2 folders)
  Photographs are of Yamin, family members, and colleagues including Bill and Maria Lipkind, and Aaron Siskind.
  - Photographs of Alice and Leo Yamin, 1928-1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Photographs of Family Members and Friends, including Aaron Siskind, 1923-1952, undated (Box 2, Folder 79)